Mss.Rec.126 Mss.Rec.126
American Philosophical Society
Interviews concerning the paintings of the Seneca artist Ernest Smith
1973
Mss.Rec.126
American Philosophical Society
11.0 Reel(s)
Interviews and discussions with the Seneca artist Ernest Smith on his paintings of Seneca customs, stories, ceremonies, crafts, food preparation, and other traditional ways. Smith was a Seneca from the Tonawanda Reservation in New York state. The paintings were done in the 1930s and are presently in the Rochester Museum and Science Center in Rochester, New York. The recordings were made by William N. Fenton and his student, Jeanette Collamer, in 1973 at the museum in Rochester. The paintings are referred to on the recordings by the museum's catalog numbers for the paintings. Some of the paintings do not have assigned titles. Sound quality is fair overall, with severe distortion and prominent background noise on the final tape.
11 sound tape reels (29 hr., 41 min.): analog, 1 7/8 ips, 1/2 track, mono; 5 in.
Collamer, Jeanette
Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005
Smith, Ernest
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by William N. Fenton in 1985.
Related materials
William N. Fenton Papers (Mss.Ms.Coll.20)
Arrangement note
Contents of tapes 1 and 2 (original tape numbers 1 and 1A) are identical. Tape 2 not transferred to DAT.
Indian artists; Seneca art; Seneca Indians--Folklore; Seneca Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Seneca Indians--Social life and customs; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Interview with Ernest Smith, 3-12-1973 [1 of 2], 1973-03-12; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:47:10; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
    Scope and Contents note
    Interview with Seneca artist Ernest Smith regarding his paintings held at the Rochester Museum. The paintings are referred to by their Museum catalog numbers.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca dance; Seneca Indians--Folklore; Seneca Indians--Rites and ceremonies
  - Interview with Ernest Smith, 3-12-1973 [2 of 2], 1973-03-12; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:43:33; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
    Handsome Lake, 1735-1815; Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca dance; Seneca Indians--Folklore; Seneca Indians--Rites and ceremonies
  - Interview with Ernest Smith, 3-13-1973 [1 of 3], 1973-03-13; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:46:27; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
    Lacrosse; Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca dance; Seneca Indians--Folklore
  - Interview with Ernest Smith, 3-13-1973 [2 of 3], 1973-03-13; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:56:03; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
    Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca Indians--Folklore
  - Interview with Ernest Smith, 3-13-1973 [3 of 3], 1973-03-13; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:55:00; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
    Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca Indians--Folklore; Seneca Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Seneca pottery; Wampum
  - Interview with Ernest Smith, 3-14-1973, 1973-03-14; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:27:18; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
    Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca Indians--Domestic life; Seneca Indians--Folklore; Seneca Indians--Material culture
  - Interview with Ernest Smith, 3-15-1973 [1 of 2], 1973-03-15; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:27:33; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
    Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca Indians--Folklore; Seneca Indians--Material culture
  - Interview with Ernest Smith, 3-15-1973 [2 of 2], 1973-03-15; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:45:11; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
    Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca Indians--Folklore; Seneca Indians--Material culture; Seneca Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Wampum
  - 1935-1936, Oils and Large Water Colors
    - Interview with Ernest Smith, 3-16-1973, 1973-03-16; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:43:36; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
      Fox Indians; Rochester (N.Y.); Sauk Indians; Seneca art; Seneca dance; Seneca Indians--Folklore
  - Economic Activities
    - Interview with Ernest Smith, Paintings of Economic Activities, 4-16-1973 [1 of 2], 1973-04-16; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 02:00:05; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
      Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca Indians--Domestic life; Seneca Indians--Material culture
    - Interview with Ernest Smith, Paintings of Economic Activities, 4-16-1973 [2 of 2], 1973-04-16; 07-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:59:33; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
      Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca Indians--Domestic life; Seneca Indians--Folklore; Seneca pottery
  - Interview with Ernest Smith, 4-17-1973 [1 of 2], 1973-04-17; 08-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:35:51; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
    Lacrosse; Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca Indians--Folklore
  - Interview with Ernest Smith, 4-17-1973 [2 of 2], 1973-04-17; 08-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:41:49; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
  - Mythology
    - Interview with Ernest Smith, Paintings of Mythology, 4-18-1973, 1973-04-18; 09-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:32:58; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
  - Ceremonies and Dances
    - Interview with Ernest Smith, Paintings of Ceremonies and Dances, 4-18-1973, 1973-04-18; 09-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:51:51; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
      Rochester (N.Y.); Seneca art; Seneca dance; Seneca Indians--Folklore; Seneca Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Wampum
    - Interview with Ernest Smith, Paintings of Ceremonies and Dances, 4-19-1973 [1 of 2], 1973-04-19; 10-01; 1.0 .mp3; 02:01:40; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
    - Interview with Ernest Smith, Paintings of Ceremonies and Dances, 4-19-1973 [2 of 2], 1973-04-19; 10-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:46:31; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
  - Interview with Ernest Smith [1 of 2], 1973-04; 11-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:35:33; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest
    Discussions with Ernest Smith regarding Flute Player, Courting Flute, Fish Dance Song, Burnin [sic] Springs, Stories to Scare Children (Long Nose, Legs, Flapping Ears). A very distorted program, with prominent uncorrected background noise.
  - Interview with Ernest Smith [2 of 2], 1973-04; 11-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:38:56; Collamer, Jeanette; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Smith, Ernest